A Guide to the Records of the Virginia Office of the Secretary of Education, 2001-2010 (bulk 2005-2009)
Library of Virginia
- VIII. Special Projects and Governor's Initiatives, 2002-2010., Extent: 5.68 cubic feet (13 boxes). (Box 40-52)
  - Subseries VIII.C. High School Reform Initiatives, 2002-2007., Extent: 0.88 cubic feet (3 boxes).
    This subseries is housed in three boxes. In June 2005, Virginia received a National Governors Association (NGA) Honor States Grant to implement redesign initiatives to improve graduation rates and college readiness. The goals of the grant were: decreasing ninth and tenth grade retention in high school, increasing mathematics proficiency, decreasing the number of high school dropouts, increasing the number of high school graduates, increasing college readiness of high school graduates by reducing the number of developmental courses taken by recent graduates, increasing the number of students who immediately attend college, and increasing college graduation rates. This policy initiative continued in the Kaine administration.
    Many of these records appear to belong to Sarah Finley, Deputy of Secretary of Education (2002-2005) and Kendall Tyree, Special Assistant to the Secretary of Education. Box 46, folders 5-7 contain Tyree's notes and meeting agendas for many of the Warner and Kaine administration's education initiatives.
    - Achieve, Inc., New Diploma Project, 2005. (Box 44, Folder 1)
    - ACT, Virginia Data, Preparing Students for College and Work, 2004. (Box 44, Folder 2)
    - Education Commission of the States (ECS), Closing the College Gap, Virginia Data, April 2003. (Box 44, Folder 3)
    - Southern Regional Education Board (SREB), ACT and SAT Scores, 2003. (Box 44, Folder 4)
    - High Schools and Beyond, undated. (Box 44, Folder 5)
    - High School Research, 2003. (Box 44, Folder 6)
    - Newsweek, America's Best High Schools, 2 June 2003. (Box 44, Folder 7)
    - School-College Alignment, 2003. (Box 44, Folder 8)
    - High School Reform Reports (1 of 6), 2004. (Box 44, Folder 9)
    - High School Reform Reports (2 of 6), 2004. (Box 44, Folder 10)
    - High School Reform Reports (3 of 6), 2004. (Box 44, Folder 11)
    - High School Reform Reports (4 of 6), 2004. (Box 44, Folder 12)
    - High School Reform Reports (5 of 6), 2004-2005. (Box 45, Folder 1)
    - High School Reform Reports (6 of 6), 2004. (Box 45, Folder 2)
    - Grade Nine: The Make It or Break It Year, 19-20 February 2002
      - Overview (Box 45, Folder 3)
      - Robert Lynn Canady (Box 45, Folder 4)
      - Sarah Armstrong (Box 45, Folder 5)
      - Jerry Bourdeaux (Box 45, Folder 6)
      - Luke Fennell (Box 45, Folder 7)
      - Kevin Flanigan (Box 45, Folder 8)
      - Elaine Fogliani (Box 45, Folder 9)
      - Seibert, Moore and Habeeb (Box 45, Folder 10)
      - Deborah Haver Hutchens (Box 45, Folder 11)
      - Laura McCullough (Box 45, Folder 12)
      - Deborah Pettit (Box 45, Folder 13)
      - Pamela Roland (Box 45, Folder 14)
      - Kathleen Owings Swan (Box 45, Folder 15)
    - High School Exit Exams
      - Center for Education Policy (CEP), State High School Exit Exams: A Challenging Year (volume), August 2006. (Box 45)
      - Center for Education Policy (CEP), State High School Exit Exams: States Try Harder, But Gaps Exist (volume), August 2005. (Box 45)
      - American Youth Policy Forum, High School Redesign for State Policy Leaders: Boston, 12-14 March 2006. (Box 45, Folder 16)
    - Virginia Community College System (VCSS), Career and Technical Education (CTE) Dual Enrollment and Articulation
      - VCCS, 1st Dual Enrollment Articulation, 2002-2003. (Box 46, Folder 1)
      - Dual Enrollment Articulation Agreements, 2002-2003. (Box 46, Folder 2)
      - Virginia Beach Advanced Technology Center, 2002. (Box 46, Folder 3)
      - VCCS, Competency Based Education: The Framework for Tech Prep Curricula, undated. (Box 46, Folder 4)
    - Kendall Tyree's Notebook on Warner and Kaine Administration Education Initiatives
      - 2004-2007 (Box 46, Folder 5)
      - 2004-2005 (Box 46, Folder 6)
      - 2005 (Box 46, Folder 7)
  - Subseries VIII.D. Achieve: American Diploma Project (ADP), 2006-2008., Extent: 1.05 cubic feet (3 boxes).
    This subseries is housed in three boxes. Achieve is a nonprofit education organization created to support standards-based education reform efforts across the states. In 2005, Achieve launched the American Diploma Project (ADP) Network in order to make college readiness a priority in the states. ADP Network states were committed to improving "postsecondary preparation by aligning high school standards, graduation requirements and assessment and accountability systems with the demands of college and careers." ADP focused on aligning high school standards and assessments with the knowledge and skills needed for college and careers; establishing a college- and career-ready curriculum to prepare high school graduates for post secondary education; and developing statewide high school assessment benchmarks in mathematics and English. As part of ADP, Virginia participated in Achieve's Alignment Institute Initiative. As part of this initiative, Virginia conducted a higher education survey for college readiness with a focus on essential English and mathematic skills required by Virginia institutions. Deputy Secretary of Education Judy Heiman and Special Assistant Kendall Tyree worked on ADP.
    - Achieve Data Profile: Virginia, 2007. (Box 47, Folder 1)
    - Achieve Alignment Institute, Minneapolis Meeting, 2007. (Box 47, Folder 2)
    - Achieve Alignment Institute, Dallas Meeting (part one), 26-28 March 2007. (Box 47, Folder 3)
    - Achieve Alignment Institute, Dallas Meeting (part two), 26-28 March 2007. (Box 47, Folder 4)
    - Achieve Alignment Institute, Dallas Meeting (part three), 26-28 March 2007. (Box 47, Folder 5)
    - Virginia's Participation in the Achieve Alignment Institute Initiative, 2007. (Box 47, Folder 6)
    - Virginia College and University Admission Requirements (part one), 2007. (Box 47, Folder 7)
    - Virginia College and University Admission Requirements (part two), 2007. (Box 47, Folder 8)
    - Virginia University Competencies, undated. (Box 48, Folder 1)
    - ADP Benchmarks with the Virginia Mathematics Standards of Learning and Curriculum Framework, undated. (Box 48, Folder 2)
    - Essential Mathematics Skills Needed for Entry-Level College Courses (surveys, B-L), 2007. (Box 48, Folder 3)
    - Essential Mathematics Skills Needed for Entry-Level College Courses (surveys, M-T), 2007. (Box 48, Folder 4)
    - Essential Mathematics Skills Needed for Entry-Level College Courses (surveys, U-W), 2007. (Box 48, Folder 5)
    - Essential English Skills Needed for Entry-Level College Courses (surveys, B-M), 2007. (Box 48, Folder 6)
    - Essential English Skills Needed for Entry-Level College Courses (surveys, N-U), 2007. (Box 49, Folder 1)
    - Essential English Skills Needed for Entry-Level College Courses (surveys, V-W), 2007. (Box 49, Folder 2)
    - Achieve Data Profile: Virginia, April 2006. (Box 49, Folder 3)
    - Creating a High School Diploma that Counts: Lessons from the ADP Network, 5 January 2007. (Box 49, Folder 4)
    - Miscellaneous Achieve Reports, 2007-2008. (Box 49, Folder 5)
  - Subseries VIII.E. Workforce Development, 2006-2010., Extent: 0.35 cubic feet (1 box).
    This subseries is housed in one box and is arranged in chronological order. On 21 March 2006, Governor Tim Kaine named Daniel C. LeBlanc, former President of the Virginia AFL-CIO and Kaine's failed nominee for Secretary of the Commonwealth, as Senior Advisor to the Governor for Workforce. Executive Order 25 issued by Governor Kaine on 23 June 2006 delegated his authority as Chief Workforce Development Officer to the Senior Advisor to the Governor for Workforce and further clarified the Advisor's duties and responsibilities. This order was issued to ensure that initial transition steps occurred to implement the 2006 legislation. Kaine's Executive Order 61, issued on 4 January 2008, rescinded Executive Order 25 and was issued to ensure that the next phase of transition occurred including: the creation of a Workforce Sub-Cabinet to ensure Cabinet collaboration regarding workforce development as required by state and federal statute; listing of the duties of the Cabinet Secretaries and designating the Virginia Community College System (VCCS) as the designated state agency for the WIA, including that of grant recipient and fiscal administrative agency. This subseries includes meeting material for Workforce Sub-Cabinet meetings (agendas, handouts, and notes) attended by Secretary of Education Tom Morris and other workforce related records.
    - Virginia Workforce Council Meeting, 8 June 2006. (Box 50, Folder 1)
    - Reference Material, 2006. (Box 50, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, 2007. (Box 50, Folder 2)
    - Workforce Development Strategy and Consolidation, 2007. (Box 50, Folder 3)
    - Workforce Sub-Cabinet Meeting, 23 January 2007. (Box 50, Folder 4)
    - Workforce Sub-Cabinet Meeting, 8 February 2007. (Box 50, Folder 4)
    - Workforce Sub-Cabinet Meeting, 15 February 2007. (Box 50, Folder 4)
    - State Workforce Meeting, 5 March 2007. (Box 50, Folder 4)
    - Workforce Sub-Cabinet Meeting, 24 May 2007. (Box 50, Folder 4)
    - Workforce Sub-Cabinet Meeting, 6 June 2007. (Box 50, Folder 5)
    - Workforce Sub-Cabinet Meeting, 14 June 2007. (Box 50, Folder 5)
    - Workforce Sub-Cabinet Meeting, 5 July 2007. (Box 50, Folder 5)
    - Workforce Sub-Cabinet Material, July-August 2007. (Box 50, Folder 5)
    - Workforce Sub-Cabinet Meetings, September-December 2007. (Box 50, Folder 5)
    - Virginia Workforce Council Meeting, 4 January 2008. (Box 50, Folder 6)
    - Workforce Sub-Cabinet Meetings, February-August 2008. (Box 50, Folder 7)
    - Reference Material, 2007-2008. (Box 50, Folder 8)
    - Reference Material, 2008. (Box 50, Folder 9)
    - Workforce Sub-Cabinet Meetings, March-June 2009. (Box 50, Folder 10)
    - Workforce Letters, 2009. (Box 50, Folder 10)
    - Virginia Workforce Council Meeting, 7 January 2010. (Box 50, Folder 10)
    - Grow Your Own: A Workforce Pipeline, Central Virginia Community College, 2007. (Box 50, Folder 11)
  - Subseries VIII.F. Teacher Quality, 2006., Extent: 2.0 cubic feet (3 boxes).
    This subseries is housed in two boxes and is arranged in alphabetical order by school division. Teacher evaluation was one of three teacher quality initiatives by the Kaine administration (teachers' salaries and teacher recruitment and retention were the other two). The primary purpose of teacher evaluation is to improve instruction and enhance student achievement by providing timely and meaningful feedback and support to the teacher. Evaluation is also a mechanism for professional growth and development. Teacher evaluation should be one part of a larger system that fosters learning communities in schools by creating supportive structures that enhance student achievement, teacher growth and retention. Such structures include a quality induction program with mentoring of new teachers, embedded professional development focused on teacher and school goals, effective and supportive leadership and a collaborative environment that encourages collegiality and teamwork. This subseries contains the established policies and practices for evaluation by each school division submitted to the Secretary of Education as required by legislation passed in 2006.
    - Accomack County-Hopewell, 2006. (Box 51)
    - Isle of Wight County-York County, 2006. (Box 52)